<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Joshua Russell on Joshua Russell</title>
    <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Joshua Russell on Joshua Russell</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Listening for patterns in the Earth</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/talk/brown_amnh_2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/talk/brown_amnh_2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NoMelt: seismic constraints on oceanic lithosphere petrofabric</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/research/nomelt/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/research/nomelt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;p style=&#34;float:right;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;featured.jpg&#34; width=&#34;400px&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt; Seismic anisotropy offers perhaps the most direct observational window into convection in Earth&amp;rsquo;s mantle as well as the structure and formation of oceanic plates. The NoMelt experiment, located ~1000 km southeast of Hawaii, was designed to better understand the fundamental plate tectonic processes involved in the formation and evolution of oceanic plates by looking at a region far from complications due to upwelling or subduction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
I use surface waves from ambient seismic noise recorded on ocean bottom seismometers (OBS) at NoMelt to measure both azimuthal and polarization anisotropy. For the first time, we are able to observe the complete anisotropic complexity of surface waves, including Love wave anisotropy. This allows us to completely characterize the elastic structure of the oceanic lithosphere and compare it with handsample petrofabrics, bridging the gap between hand seismic and outcrop length scales.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OBSrange: A new tool for the precise location of ocean bottom seismometers</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/research/obs_range/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/research/obs_range/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;featured.jpg&#34; width=&#34;600px&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
  &lt;font color=&#34;gray&#34;&gt;
  &lt;small&gt;
      Fig 1. Schematic showing the rangining procedure for location ocean bottom seismometers (OBS) on the seafloor [Russell et al., 2018].
  &lt;/small&gt;
  &lt;/font&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly all seismological analyses require accurate knowledge of the instrument location. Furthermore, successful recovery of OBS from the seafloor rely on our ability to locate them. Together with &lt;a href=&#34;http://zeilon.squarespace.com/&#34;&gt;Zach Eilon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href =&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Stephen_Mosher&#34;&gt;Stephen Mosher&lt;/a&gt;, I have developed a new open-source tool called OBSrange for locating ocean bottom seismometers on the seafloor and providing statistically robust uncertainties. We applied the tool to data from the 2018 Young Pacific ORCA deployment, revealing a clockwise mesoscale eddy that correlates with observed ocean currents in the region. This novel measurement of depth integrated flow through the water column is the first of its kind and could potentially be used to calibrate models of vertical shear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;gyre.jpg&#34; width=&#34;1000px&#34;&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
  &lt;font color=&#34;gray&#34;&gt;
  &lt;small&gt;
      Fig 2. Drift patterns of the 30 OBS of the 2018 Young Pacific Orca deployment. A clockwise mesoscale gyre can be observed that correlates in space and time with geostrophic flow patterns.
  &lt;/small&gt;
  &lt;/font&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pathways Into Geophysics and Seismology</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/talk/iris_recruitment/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/talk/iris_recruitment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In recent years, an effort has been made to broaden the geosciences both in terms of the number of underrepresented minorities as well as students with backgrounds in math, physics, and computer science. As an alumnus of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iris.edu/hq/internship/blogs/user/80&#34;&gt;IRIS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://resess.unavco.org/people/alumni/2014/russell/russell.html&#34;&gt;UNAVCO RESESS&lt;/a&gt; emersive undergraduate research programs, I serve as one of the 2018 IRIS recruitment speakers as part of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iris.edu/hq/internship/recruitment&#34;&gt;IRIS Recruitment Lecture Series&lt;/a&gt;. In this role, I travel to minority-serving institutions to speak to undergraduates in the geosciences, mathematics, physics, and computer science about geophysics and seismology career paths as well as opportunities that are available for undergraduate research. See below for the flyer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;IRIS_lecture.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;IRIS Lecture&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research As Art</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/other/research_as_art/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/other/research_as_art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Under construction&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing Earth&#39;s Free Oscillations</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/other/normal_modes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/other/normal_modes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/215665951&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;360&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/215665951&#34;&gt;EarthVibrations&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com/seismicsoundlab&#34;&gt;seismicsoundlab&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://vimeo.com&#34;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a large earthquake, waves bounce around inside the earth for hours and sometimes days. These audio-visualizations show how these waves travel along the surface of the earth, displayed as a ring. This 2-dimensional ring is made up of 2,000 points on the earth&amp;rsquo;s surface that display ground motion after an earthquake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Audiovisual of the M6.9 earthquake that occurred off the coast of Fiji on 2/24/2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VISUAL: Synthetic seismograms were generated at 2000 points on the earth&amp;rsquo;s surface using Instaseis. Both the vertical (Z) and radial &amp;reg; components are visualized, resulting in elliptical patterns. Can you spot the Rayleigh waves?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AUDIO: We are listening to the antipode (bottom of the circle) where our &amp;ldquo;microphone&amp;rdquo; is denoted by the red circle. The seismogram at the antipode is sonified using a new resynthesis technique that captures frequency content of the waveform more accurately than direct sonification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Audiovisual demonstration where traveling waves are generated by the sum of many standing waves (normal modes) at the Earth&amp;rsquo;s surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VIDEO: shows 9 of Earth&amp;rsquo;s observable lowest frequency normal modes (color rings) with tones corresponding to the center frequency of each mode. Higher frequency modes are represented by cool colors and low frequencies by warm colors. The outer ring (white) represents the sum of the colored rings. Can you spot the waves traveling through the ring?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AUDIO: The loudness of each tone is modulated by its amplitude envelope. Notice how the chord evolves over time as the higher frequencies die away.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on radial anisotropy of ~70 Ma oceanic lithosphere</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/talk/ssw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/talk/ssw/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;group.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;SSW 2017 Group Picture&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on radial anisotropy in the central Pacific upper mantle from the NoMelt OBS array</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/talk/agu_2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/talk/agu_2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
