<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Researches on Joshua Russell</title>
    <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Researches on Joshua Russell</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jbrussell.github.io/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Wave propagation: Love wave Overtone interference</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/research/love_overtones/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/research/love_overtones/</guid>
      <description> UNDER CONSTRUCTION&amp;hellip; </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ENAM: Seismic anisotropy offshore eastern North America</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/research/enam/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/research/enam/</guid>
      <description> UNDER CONSTRUCTION&amp;hellip; </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NoMelt: seismic constraints on oceanic lithosphere petrofabric</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/research/nomelt/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/research/nomelt/</guid>
      <description>Seismic anisotropy offers perhaps the most direct observational window into convection in Earth&amp;rsquo;s mantle as well as the structure and formation of oceanic plates. The NoMelt experiment, located ~1000 km southeast of Hawaii, was designed to better understand the fundamental plate tectonic processes involved in the formation and evolution of oceanic plates by looking at a region far from complications due to upwelling or subduction.  I use surface waves from ambient seismic noise recorded on ocean bottom seismometers (OBS) at NoMelt to measure both azimuthal and polarization anisotropy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OBSrange: A new tool for the precise location of ocean bottom seismometers</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/research/obs_range/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/research/obs_range/</guid>
      <description>Fig 1. Schematic showing the rangining procedure for location ocean bottom seismometers (OBS) on the seafloor [Russell et al., 2018].     Nearly all seismological analyses require accurate knowledge of the instrument location. Furthermore, successful recovery of OBS from the seafloor rely on our ability to locate them. Together with Zach Eilon and Stephen Mosher, I have developed a new open-source tool called OBSrange for locating ocean bottom seismometers on the seafloor and providing statistically robust uncertainties.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>