<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Earth Institute LIVE 2020 on Joshua Russell</title>
    <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Earth Institute LIVE 2020 on Joshua Russell</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Additional Resources</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/resources/</guid>
      <description>Download the full GitHub repository for this lesson here:  
 The complete Earth Institute LIVE K-12 Series:
https://www.earth.columbia.edu/videos/channel/k12-education
 Additional bokeh and holoviews examples that use earthquake data: http://examples.holoviews.org/Earthquake_Visualization.html
http://philippjfr.com/blog/visualizing-earthquake-data-with-holoviews-and-bokeh/
 More on seismic noise reduction due to COVID-19:
https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-00965-x
 On electricity consumption and economic recession:
https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/04/08/upshot/electricity-usage-predict-coronavirus-recession.html
  Tools for educators  More data sonification by Ben Holtzman can be found at the Seismic Sound Lab homepage:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Earthquake Magnitude and Depth</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/part1a3_magnitudedepth/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/part1a3_magnitudedepth/</guid>
      <description>Magnitude and depth are two basic features of an earthquake that are important for understanding plate tectonics as well as earthquake hazard. Typically, the shallower the earthquake and larger the magnitude, the more potential for destruction.
In the two interactive figures below, we will explore relationships between earthquake magnitude and depth using what&amp;rsquo;s called &amp;ldquo;linking and brushing&amp;rdquo;. Selecting data in one figure will highlight the corresponding points in the other.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Global Seismicity</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/part1a1_globalearthquakes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/part1a1_globalearthquakes/</guid>
      <description>Hundreds of earthquakes occur across the globe every day, but most of them are too small for us to feel. Here, we will dive into earthquake data and explore some of the larger magnitude earthquakes (greater than M5.0) that have occurred over the past several years.
We start by looking at where earthquakes occur spatially. The interactive map below shows the past 5 years of earthquakes, where each circle represents a single earthquake.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2011 Tohoku Earthquake</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/part2b_tohoku2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/part2b_tohoku2011/</guid>
      <description>INTRO
In this section, we will listen to seismic data at the 3 stations shown in the map below. They represent close, intermediate, and far distances from the earthquake epicenter.
 The Background Noise Before we listen to the earthquakes, we will first listen to the background noise levels at one of the three stations, P39A, in Salisbury, MO.
 What do you notice about the background noise? Are there any dominant frequencies?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making Your Own Maps With trinket.io</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/part1a2_makeyourown/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/part1a2_makeyourown/</guid>
      <description>Now we will use trinket.io to make our own earthquake maps with Python. Trinkets allow you to run snippets of Python code directly in your internet browser! Just click the  button in the top bar to run the code.

Starting simple Our first example is a simple sinusoid with frequency $f$ and amplitude $A$:
$$ y = A \sin (f x) $$
Try making changes to the code and rerunning it to see how the output changes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seismic Noise in New York City</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/part1b_seismicnoisenyc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/part1b_seismicnoisenyc/</guid>
      <description>Anyone who has been to New York City knows it can be a noisy place. The same goes for the ground beneath our feet as cars, trucks, buses, and subways rumble by. Extremely sensitive seismometers that measure ground motion can detect these vibrations. Due to the COVID-19 crisis and the resulting shelter-in-place protocols active around the world, seismic noise has noticeably decreased worldwide.
Shown below is data from a seismometer currently installed in Central Park as part of the Lamont-Doherty Cooperative Seismographic Network (LCSN).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Sounds of NYC</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/part2c_noisenyc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/part2c_noisenyc/</guid>
      <description>Finally, we return to the ground vibrations measured in Central Park that we looked at in section Seismic Noise in NYC. However, because we need a waveform that oscillates around zero in order to turn it into sound, we remove the daily running average from the hourly measurements. The resulting waveform and spectrogram is shown below.
The daily signal is the main feature of the waveform and appears as a bright streak in the spectrogram at around 100 Hz in sonified frequency (This is 1 / 24 hours = 1 / 86,400 seconds $\approx$ $1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Turning Data Into Sound</title>
      <link>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/part2a_sonification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jbrussell.github.io/eilive2020/part2a_sonification/</guid>
      <description>The human ear is hardwired to find patterns within complex sounds. Together with visual cues, we can use data sonification &amp;mdash; or turning data into sound &amp;mdash; to extract new information from complicated datasets that may be missed by just looking at the data. The Seismic Sound Lab at the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory works to combine both senses with audio-visuals in order to learn new things about the Earth as well as to communicate that knowledge to the general public.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>